Part 1 - The context

Accessibility matters

Accessibility means that tools, technologies, websites, ebooks and digital documents are designed and developed so that everyone, regardless of their disabilities - physical, cognitive, motor, permanent or temporary, situational or age-related - can use them. Accessibility is fundamental to providing equal access to information, study, entertainment, and equal opportunities also to people with disabilities.

In addition to being required by the regulatory frameworks in force in many countries around the world, accessibility is a social value and a basic human right recognized by the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities (UN CRPD).

Accessibility is also good for business: an accessible tool, website or ebook is a product of high quality that improves the general user experience and satisfaction[1].

Be prepared for June 2025: the European Accessibility Act is approaching

The European Accessibility Act is an EU Directive (2019/882)[2] that aims to improve the functioning of the internal market for accessible products and services, by removing barriers created by divergent rules in Member States. It will enter into force in June 2025. The Directive establishes binding accessibility targets that must be met by many different products and services to strengthen the rights of people with disabilities to access goods and services, including ebooks. Since ebooks are considered a service, the concept of a service provider now includes publishers and all the other economic operators involved in their distribution. Every step of the publishing chain must integrate accessibility to create an accessible digital publishing ecosystem.

For publishers, this means that they are required to produce their digital publications in an accessible format, according to the born accessible paradigm.

The white paper “E-books for all - Towards an accessible digital ecosystem” by Fondazione LIA[3] provides detailed information on the impact of the EAA on the publishing supply chain.

The European ebook market, however, is not only made up of new titles, which can be placed on the market already accessible, but also of ebooks that have been published in previous years, and which publishers will have to make accessible if they want to keep them on the European market.

The ABE Lab project

The partners

The ABE Lab - Accessible Backlist Ebooks Laboratory is a European Cooperation project funded by Creative Europe. The project is coordinated by the European Digital Reading Lab (EDRLab); Fondazione LIA and the National Library of the Netherlands (Koninklijke Bibliotheek - KB) are partners.

EDRLab is a non-profit transnational laboratory that develops open standards and open-source tools, to accelerate the diffusion of digital technologies in the publishing industry. It is an association of more than 70 members from the publishing industry, including publishers, providers of publishing services, distributors, tools developers and accessibility specialists. It is also the developer of the Thorium Reader application, a free and highly accessible reading application for EPUB 3 ebooks[4].

Fondazione LIA is an Italian non-profit organisation and an internationally recognized expert in the certification of accessibility of EPUB 3 ebooks, having already certified more than 30.000 ebooks available in the libri italiani accessibili catalogue[5]. Fondazione LIA carries out research and development activities in the field of digital accessibility, organises awareness-raising events, offers training courses and consulting activities. It works with 76 publishing imprints to create and distribute the new ebooks as born accessible publications and it’s part of an international network of organisations dealing with accessibility of contents[6].

KB - The National Library of the Netherlands has a long history in library research and promotes the visibility, usability and longevity of the Dutch Library Collection, defined as the collective holdings of all publicly funded libraries in the Netherlands. It has three main roles: it is the national depot where many Dutch publishers send their ebooks, it operates an ebook lending platform for all Dutch public libraries and it commissions the conversion of non-accessible (e)books to accessible formats for people with a print impairment. With the EAA on the horizon, the KB strives to get all of its public services accessible[7].

Both EDRLab and LIA are part of the W3C Publishing Business Group, W3C Publishing Working Group, W3C EPUB Community Group, and are active members of the EPUB Community Group Accessibility Task Force and of the EPUB Community Group Fixed Layout Accessibility Task Force.

Objectives and outcomes of the project

ABE Lab has two main objectives:

to collect and analyse in detail the composition of the European ebook backlist
to provide guidelines to European publishers to boost the remediation of the ebooks from their backlist.

Without precise data about the composition of the ebook backlist in Europe, it is not possible to evaluate the best workflows and estimate the time and expertise that making these ebooks accessible would require. The first part of the project was therefore focused on the collection and analysis of data to define the size and composition of the European ebook backlist - defined as the collection of all ebooks available on the EU market - and on identifying the most recurrent accessibility issues that can be found in these ebooks. The results are detailed in the public deliverable Report on Backlist Data and gap analysis, freely downloadable from the official ABE Lab website both in PDF and EPUB format. An online version is also available[8].

The core part of the project has been to analyse and test the processes and workflows by which ebooks of different types and formats can be transformed into accessible EPUB files or accessible PDF files. This implies knowing which remediation tools are available on the market and what they can do, for which formats and types of books (fiction, complex layouts, STEM) they are most effective and which are their shortcomings.

It will in fact be essential to have tools that are able to correct the accessibility errors identified in the backlist files, or that can offer the human operators options and features to support them in their ebook remediation journey.

Consequently, testing the remediation tools has represented a fundamental part of ABE Lab. The results of the tests carried out in the context of the project form the basis of these guidelines.

All public future deliverables of the project will be available, after publication, on the Deliverables page[9] of the ABE Lab website.

Objectives of the guidelines

To the best of our knowledge, this white paper represents the first publicly-available work of its kind. The document outlines high-level guidelines that stakeholders, producers and developers of technological tools and solutions aimed at fixing the accessibility issues of digital documents and publications can use to independently evaluate their tools. It can also be a useful resource to improve them through the integration of new features, or to design new ones that offer the functionalities and support necessary to produce fully accessible ebooks starting from inaccessible versions. Remediation tools should provide all the possible support for the human operators responsible for the file correction activity, making the process as simple, intuitive and fluid as possible. This, of course, will depend also on the competences of the target users and on the type of tool used - remediation tools can be desktop applications, cloud platforms, API, SDK and more.

The information these guidelines provide are based on the accessibility requirements for ebooks defined by the European Accessibility Act listed in Annex I sections III and IV Linea f). EPUB (Electronic PUBlications)[10] is recognized as the format of choice to respond to those requirements, as detailed by the EPUB Accessibility - EU Accessibility Act Mapping[11]. Therefore, the EPUB Accessibility represents the target for the remediation of ebooks in EPUB format, since EPUB files conforming to EPUB Accessibility guidelines are responding to the European Accessibility Act requirements. The EPUB Accessibility guidelines are built on the Web Content Accessibility Guidelines 2(WCAG 2)[12], which they include and expand with specific requirements for digital publications.

Ebooks, however, are not exclusively produced in EPUB format. Other formats coexist, most of them derived from this main format or based on the same web technologies (HTML, JavaScript, CSS) [13].

A notable exception to this is the Portable Document Format (PDF), a format initially proposed for print reliability and digital conservation of documents. Accessibility of PDF is based on WCAG 2 and is made possible thanks to an additional semantic descriptive layer composed of 28 elements expressed as XML language tags. The PDF/UA ISO ^14 standard provides definitive terms and requirements for accessibility in PDF documents and applications.

Pre-paginated ebooks (like PDFs and Fixed Layout EPUBs) do not comply with the EAA requirements for the criterion of flexibility and choice in the presentation of the content, a key functionality for persons facing cognitive difficulties (like dyslexia) or with sight impairments. Hence, to make the content of a PDF fully accessible, a change of format might be necessary, from a fixed layout one to a reflowable one.

A rapidly evolving landscape

Technology providers and developers of technical tools for the publishing industry are increasingly integrating functionalities in their products and IT solutions that can be used to convert existing inaccessible digital files into accessible digital versions, or to enhance their level of accessibility. Some tools already exist on the market with this aim, and we are also aware of several new projects in development. It is therefore easy to predict that more dedicated technological solutions will be made available in the near future.

This rapidly evolving landscape is also driven by an increasingly widespread use of new types of automation powered by systems based on Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning, whose great potential could play a key role in improving and speeding up processes for correcting accessibility issues - in particular, they represent a possible solution to quickly process large amounts of files.

The rapid advance of Artificial Intelligence

When we defined the objectives and activities of the ABE Lab project, the topic of Artificial Intelligence was not yet as hot a topic as it would become just a few months later. Artificial Intelligence applied to an ever-increasing number of fields began to be talked about very widely during the course of the project. Therefore, the study of the use of Artificial Intelligence in the context of digital accessibility and in particular its correction - i.e., in remediation tools - was not among the aims of the ABE Lab project.

Publishers and other actors in the publishing chain have been using automation, including Natural Language Processing and Artificial Intelligence technologies, for several years already. Now facing the revolutions of Large Language Models (LLM) and Generative AI technologies (GAI), they are observing, testing and defining positions towards this technology and its use in editorial workflows. This has led in some cases to express concerns related to the uncertainty about how their contents and files are used by such systems.

However, it should also be highlighted that, in the current state of the art, Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning systems cannot replace the competence and evaluation ability of a human being. If it is possible, for example, to automatically generate alternative descriptions for images with AI, it has yet to be proved that these alternative descriptions can provide information equivalent to that conveyed by the images themself, or that they are comparable to those produced by a subject expert. Therefore, human decision is still key to stating whether such descriptions are appropriate or not for a given context.

Developers and technology specialists are aware of the power of AI, but they are also aware of the risks implied in and of the need for a wise and detailed study of side effects, edge cases, caveats and other surprises coming with intents to bypass human driven operations.

1. Introduction to Web Accessibility, W3C Web Accessibility Initiative (WAI),

https://www.w3.org/WAI/fundamentals/accessibility-intro/

2. See online at: https://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1202

3. E-books for all. Towards an accessible publishing ecosystem, Fondazione LIA, 2020. Available online at: https://www.fondazionelia.org/en/resources/e-books-for-all/

4. More information available on EDRLab’s official website: https://www.edrlab.org/

5. https://catalogo.fondazionelia.org/

6. More information available on Fondazione LIA’s official website: https://www.fondazionelia.org/

7. More information available on KB’s official website: https://www.kb.nl/en

8. Report on Backlist Data and gap analysis, ABE Lab, October 30, 2023. Available online at https://www.abelab.eu/outcomes/deliverables/#report-on-backlist-data-and-gap-analysis

9. The page can be found at the following link: https://www.abelab.eu/outcomes/deliverables/

10. EPUB® 3 defines a distribution and interchange format for digital publications and documents. The EPUB format provides a means of representing, packaging, and encoding structured and semantically enhanced web content — including HTML, CSS, SVG, and other resources — for distribution in a single-file container.

The publishing industry, worldwide, agrees that EPUB is the only digital book format which allows, with a few efforts, the creation of fully accessible ebooks. The standard is available online at: https://www.w3.org/TR/epub-33/

11. EPUB Accessibility - EU Accessibility Act Mapping, W3C Group Note, 27 December 2023. Available online at: https://www.w3.org/TR/epub-a11y-eaa-mapping/

12. The Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) are the international standard for web accessibility, developed and maintained by the W3C. WCAG 2.2 was published on 05 October 2023. An overview of WCAG 2 is available at: https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/

13. The backlist data analysis showed that some markets have other formats, like HTML books or apps (18% in France and 25% in Spain). Those formats are based on or derived from the same web technologies of the EPUB format, therefore they should comply with the Web Content Accessibility Guidelines too.

14. ISO 14289-1:2014, Document management applications - Electronic document file format enhancement for accessibility

Part 2 - Guidelines for remediation tools developers

The following guidelines present indications of different types: some strictly concern the functioning of the remediation tool, while others concern the information that developers should provide to allow an informed and adequate choice by those who have to fix the accessibility of the ebooks in their backlist. The applicability or otherwise of a guideline to a specific tool may depend on the technological characteristics of the tool itself - for example, for tools that work from the command line, guidelines that imply the presence of a graphical interface are not relevant. The functionalities detailed in the following sections might be implemented in a variety of ways: automatic, semi-automatic or manual.

What should a remediation tool do?

Find, fix, check: the three key aspects of accessibility remediation

To solve an accessibility problem, it is first necessary to identify it, and then understand its impact and how to correct it. To support the human operators, the remediation tool should identify the accessibility problem, report it to the users, and guide them in its correction by providing dedicated options to do so.

For the remediation to be effective, the tools should therefore:

find the accessibility issues contained in the ebook;

provide a way for correcting the identified accessibility issues, for example, via dedicated options;

check the conformance of the file to ensure the output will be valid with the file format specification and compliant with the target accessibility guidelines or standards. Accessibility checks carried out before export, or at the request of the operator, are also strategically important to ensure that the ebook does not have accessibility problems before it is exported and checked with external tools.

These activities should not be interpreted as steps that must be performed in a predefined sequence in the remediation process, but rather as three fundamental aspects that should be implemented by remediation tools to provide comprehensive support and ensure a quality output.

In-tool support

There should be attention to providing as much support as possible to guide the human operators in fixing the accessibility errors, with the aim of reducing the number of iterations needed to the minimum.

Even if some accessibility problems can be effectively solved automatically, a report of all automatic operations run should always be provided and manual evaluation and intervention should always be possible.

For actions where no automatic intervention is done, there should be guidance to allow the human operator to manually fix the accessibility issues of the files, for example providing dedicated menus, popups, options, in-tool guidance, ad-hoc functionalities.

Providing a code editor (such as an HTML editor for EPUB remediation tools) can be an option, but this solution requires the human operator to have a technical knowledge and although it can be really useful, this alone doesn’t provide it itself much guidance and support.

Improve, don't disrupt

The remediation tool must not cause a loss of information, must not add accessibility errors and must not compromise the technical integrity of the file. This may seem obvious, yet we have encountered tools whose solutions to correct accessibility errors generated others, making the file invalid; in other cases the output files, although passing the tool's internal validation, were reported by other software and applications as “corrupt” and thus not readable. In these cases it is not a question of accessibility, but rather of formal validity of the output and compliance with the standards that define the file format itself.

What about multimedia resources, scripts, forms, and formulas?

Multimedia elements (audio and video) are quite rare in digital books. The same goes for specific contents like form fields, scripts, and buttons, which could be used to create interactive components. Users of the tool need to know in advance whether audio, video, interactive forms (and therefore JavaScript) or formulas tagged with MathML are correctly imported into the tool and can also be retained in the output ebook when this content is present in the publication to be remediated. Support for these elements must be made explicit in the documentation or in the official channels of the tool, to avoid a loss of content and functionality of the ebook.

These elements must meet specific accessibility requirements. Tools that provide support for them should at least notify the human operators that such special content exists in the ebook, to allow them to find them and check them to verify if specific activities with dedicated tools are needed. In fact, making these components accessible may not be one of the purposes and functions of digital publishing dedicated tools. For example, audio and video content require a textual alternative (caption or transcription), which can be done with solutions for creating accessible multimedia content.

Whether they can be fixed in-tool or with external additional technologies, for an ebook to actually comply with accessibility requirements, audio and video, as well the other special content, must also be taken into consideration.

Maintaining the look & feel vs resetting the styles

When it comes to converting a PDF into an accessible PDF, we expect the original layout and design to be maintained: fonts, colours and graphic elements are not affected during the remediation phase, and the accessible file respects the graphics of the source file. There may be cases in which a reflowable EPUB presents graphic characteristics that would also be desired to be maintained in the accessible reflowable EPUB. Maintaining the look & feel of the inaccessible input file may not always be the desired solution for publishers, for example if the goal is to turn the PDF into an accessible reflowable EPUB.

It is therefore important to specify whether the tool removes by default all the graphic properties of the input file, thus returning black and white text and assigning predefined styles to the text components (headings, bold, italics, links, …), whether these are maintained, or whether it is possible to choose which solution to apply. In some cases, specific fonts are necessary to represent special characters. If styles are automatically removed and replaced, these characters may no longer be represented correctly, resulting in a loss of content.

Maintaining the graphics may also imply maintaining accessibility errors related to colour contrasts or the use of colour alone to convey information. To solve this problem, a possible solution is to allow manual editing of styles or provide image or graphics editors inside the tool itself or as external linked resources.

No solution is intrinsically better than the other, but the user must be informed.

Functionalities to fix accessibility issues

An ebook can contain many different types of accessibility errors. By analysing a sample of backlist files, we found that some accessibility problems recur with particular frequency[1].

Based on these results, and by analysing the characteristics of the remediation tools tested in the context of the project, we have identified a series of features that we deem important to remediate backlist ebooks.

Adding accessibility metadata

The lack of accessibility metadata, required by both EPUB Accessibility 1.1 and the EAA, is an error that was found in 100% of the backlist EPUB analysed. Accessibility metadata can be created by publishers or by a third-party certifier who checks the file and certifies it if accessible. Just as it is usually possible to set the general metadata of the document, such as title and author, it should also be possible to specify the accessibility metadata of the ebook as required by the EPUB Accessibility, therefore using the metadata defined in the Schema.org standard. In this regard, a remediation tool should:

detect missing accessibility metadata. The lack of accessibility metadata can be easily detected with an automatic check;

provide a way to add accessibility metadata . This could be done, for example, adding an “Accessibility information” section in the general metadata panel, or including a specific menu item that the human operator can activate to open a popup to add them;

allow to review accessibility metadata - this is satisfied simply by making the accessibility metadata available for the human operators in the popup to add them.

There are also other useful functionalities regarding accessibility metadata:

automatically create accessibility metadata based on the analysis of the EPUB features;

automatically check for correct accessibility metadata. This would require the tool to compare the declared values of the accessibility metadata with the actual content of the file and warn the human operators if something seems incorrect.

While accessibility metadata is a fundamental requirement for the accessibility of EPUB files, there is currently no defined standard for its support by the PDF format.

Alternative text for images

After missing accessibility metadata, this is the most common issue found in backlist files. The topic of image description is a delicate one and represents one of the greatest difficulties when it comes to accessible digital content: how can alternative image descriptions be validated? Who should write them?

We identified three functionalities that the remediation tools should offer:

detect missing alternative text. Images and graphics that are used for decorative purposes only don’t need an alternative text, but sometimes in the EPUB files what happen is that the HTML tags for the images (<img>, <svg>) are not just declared as decorative, but instead are missing the attributes required to specify the alternative text or to declare that the image is decorative, and so it is not possible to decide whether they were meant to be informative or not. In the case of the <img> tag, the alt attribute used to set the alternative text is always required and the HTML code is not well-formed if it’s missing. Warning the user about this error helps ensuring that all images either have an alternative text, or have been marked as non-informative;

provide a way to add an alternative text to images and graphical elements, and allowing to mark as decorative (or “artefact” in the PDF world) all the images and graphical elements that do not convey information and can be ignored by Assistive Technologies;

review all images. Providing a way to review all the images and the associated alternative text is extremely useful: it allows to check if all the images have been described and if all the decorative images have been marked as such. This is also helpful to check if the alternative descriptions are appropriate for the images and the context in which each image occurs.

Remediation tools should not provide placeholder image descriptions just to pass the accessibility validation. We have found out that some tools provide non-meaningful alternative texts like generic single words (example: “image”) or the image file name (example: “final26ok72.jpg”). Unfortunately, those practices have been in place since a long time ago. Implementing some search patterns may help easily identify them and point them as errors.

A particular type of textual alternative for graphic content is represented by the so-called extended descriptions. If the alternative text represents a summary description of the image, the extended descriptions can be longer and more structured, including also tables, lists and links. Extended descriptions should be used for complex images that can be found in certain categories of books, like STEM. These images must be described in detail to ensure that their content is correctly and thoroughly conveyed to users with visual impairments using screen readers and other Assistive Technologies. At the state of the art, there is no standard way to insert extended descriptions in either the EPUB and HTML-based formats, or the PDF format. The Daisy’s Best practices for authoring Extended Descriptions in EPUB[2] provide some useful guidance on the topic.

While providing an alternative text for non-decorative graphic elements is mandatory to reach compliance with the EAA and the WCAG, whether or not the image should be described with an extended description depends on the type of image and the context in which it is placed. The possibility of inserting them in the remediation phase represents an added value for the tools.

Missing or bad language tag

The WCAG requires that the language of the content - therefore of each HTML documents that make up the EPUB file, and of the PDF document -, as well as the language of words, sentences and passages of text in a different language are correctly identified, to allow user agents and Assistive Technologies to present them properly (with the right spelling and pronunciation by speech synthesis) to the end user.

This implies that:

the tool should allow to set the main language of the content;

the tool should allow to set the language of words, phrases or passages of text;

it would be ideal if it could recognize a mismatch between the declared language and the actual one, and report it to the human operators.

Open source language detection libraries and open dictionaries in different languages can be used to help identify the language of the content - both for the whole document and for single passages of text, even automatically - and report cases where a language assignment may potentially not match the actual language of the content.

If the recognition of the languages used in the content and their marking can be done automatically, then it must be specified which languages are supported and can be correctly identified.

What the tool should not do is to to set a default value for the language of the document regardless of the actual language of the contents. If this happens, it implies the tool can only be used to remediate content in that specific default language.

Headings hierarchy

The content of the ebooks, just like that of paper books, can be structured in sections, subsections, chapters or articles. The headings, generally visually stylized to stand out from the actual text, allow to recognize these parts and understand how a book is organised, what the main themes are and how they are connected. The same information must be made available also for visually impaired readers who can’t access the visual presentation of the text. Headings, just like other text components, must be tagged with the semantic tags available for the format used. Whether it is EPUB or PDF, it is necessary to use the heading tags in an appropriate way, with the appropriate level, implementing correct nesting.

Non-tagged PDF documents are commonly found, but we also identified EPUBs with missing or incorrect heading structures. The headings hierarchy must reflect the hierarchy of the publication or document, so an H2 should always be used for secondary level headings, H3 for tertiary, and so on. Headings of the same level may have different styles attached, but gaps in numbering must be avoided whenever possible, meaning that a H1 should always be followed by H2, and not H3 or a lower level.

Both for PDFs and EPUBs, the remediation tools should:

allow to identify (tag) a text as a heading of the appropriate level. No restriction should be applied to the available levels (i.e. from level 1 to level 6) since it’s not possible to know beforehand what is the structure of the ebook;

detect incorrect heading nesting. It is not required to use all the levels, but levels cannot be skipped and the hierarchy must be respected;

provide a way to review the headings hierarchy. This allows you to check whether the heading hierarchy respects the structure of the ebook and whether the headings are correctly nested.

Publication formats like EPUB files usually include more than one HTML document (the EPUB Content Document). In these cases, the readers’ expectation is that the main headings of each document reflects their position in the overall hierarchy of the publication. Which means that the first heading of an EPUB Content Document might not always be a first-level heading. Hence, for EPUB files, remediation tools must not force each EPUB Content Document to start with a first-level heading, as this might not actually reflect the right structure of the ebook.

This is different for single document formats such as PDF, where the order of headings must reflect the structure of the document.

Colour contrast

The WCAG defines minimum colour contrast ratio requirements between text and background, and between graphic elements necessary to understand the content and their backgrounds. Even if the remediation tool doesn’t allow to change the graphic appearance of the ebook - as it may happen for PDF to PDF/UA conversion tools -, it should check if the colour contrasts between the text and its background is sufficient and complies with the minimum requirements set by the WCAG. If feasible, a way should be provided to change the colours to meet the requirements.

This also applies to graphic elements necessary to understand the content.

Document title

It must be possible to set the title of a PDF, which is usually found in the document properties (or metadata) panels of PDF remediation tools and reading applications.

For EPUBs, however, the title of each individual EPUB Content Document (represented by the <title> tag) must be meaningful. Using the book title for each Content Document is neither correct nor meaningful. If this tag is automatically populated by the remediation tool, it is important to ensure that a more meaningful text is provided (for example, the first heading, or the top-level heading of the document, eventually preceded by the book's title).

To support this requirement, the remediation tool should provide the following features:

allowing to set the value for the <title> tag of each EPUB Content Document;

detecting empty <title> tags in EPUB Content Documents and additionally detecting wrong titles such as titles identical to the main title of the publication;

provide a way to review <title> tags. This means providing a way to ensure that each EPUB Content Document has a meaningful title.

The content of the <title> tag is often used by EPUB reading applications to inform the reader about their current position in the publication (functionality “Where am I?”), so it’s important it provides meaningful information.

Semantics

Semantics is fundamental for accessibility. HTML5 and the PDF standard provide a rather rich list of semantic tags, which must be used to convey the correct information to user agents, including Assistive Technologies such as screen readers and the people who use them. This is why a remediation tool should allow semantic tags to be assigned to content quickly and easily. Available semantic tags should not be limited to headings, paragraphs, and lists. The rich semantics the standards offer are much broader and should be used correctly.

1. Report on Backlist Data and gap analysis, ABELab, October 30, 2023. Available online at https://www.abelab.eu/outcomes/gap_analysis/

2.Available at https://daisy.github.io/transitiontoepub/best-practices/extended-desc/ExtendedDescriptionsBestPractices.html